<chapter>
  <banner>
    <img src="../../img/basic-production-banner.jpg"/>
  </banner>
  <head>
  <title>Basic Production and Growth Management</title>
  <author>[99]Gambit
    <email>gambitude99@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  </head>
<p>
This is part of the beginner's strategy guide for the games of 
<a href="https://springrts.com/wiki/Balanced_Annihilation">Balanced Annihilation</a> and 
<u>Tech Annihilation</u>.
It explains basic management of your economy and unit production.
</p>

<p>
Your success in the game depends strongly on you effectively utilizing your resources to:
<ul>
  <li>build military units to protect your economic potential and reduce your opponents'.</li>
  <li>build buildings that produce even more resources (growing your economy or "<b>eco</b>")</li>
</ul>
To do this you need to know about the game's production mechanics. 
This includes assisting units, avoiding stalls and excesses, queueing, growing your economy, 
	and the differences between rushing and balanced production.
We'll often refer broadly to <b>resources</b> when we really mean both <b>metal</b> and <b>energy</b>.
</p>

<section>
  <title>Income and Expenditure, Stalling and Excessing Concepts</title>
<p>
As a unit or building is being produced, the player's resources are spent continuously in order to 
  pay for the cost of those units.
If the player has adequate resources in storage to afford the unit, build progress will proceed at 
  a rate determined by the build power of the lab and all its assisters.
If the player does not have adequate resources in storage, then build progress will proceed at a much slower rate.
It will be constrained by the resource <i>income</i> of the player, since one can only spend resources
  as fast as one is harvesting them.
</p>
<p>
There is a situation where the player has adequate resources of one type (e.g. metal) but not of another type (e.g. energy).
This is called a <b>stall</b> since build progress will be slowed to the rate of income of the depleted resource.
Stalls are generally considered a bad thing because it means that you have resource of one type that can't be
  spent quickly, and are hindered only by a single type of resource that could be built out.
Another related concept is that of <b>leaking excess</b> or "<b>excessing</b>" resources.
If your build power is too weak and you cannot spend your resources quickly enough, they will accumulate until
  you have reached maximum capacity for that resource, at which point you will lose that income.
This is also considered bad because it means that this lost resource cannot be used at a later time, even if you
  increase your build power.
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Beginner's Build Order, or Getting On Your Feet</title>
<p>
You start the game with a single unit: the <b>commander</b>. <uniticon name="armcom"/>
This unit can build all of your basic structures including your first lab.
The lab can then build constructor units that can create even more structures.
It is common at the start of the game to queue the production of 2-3 <b>metal extractors (mexes)</b> <uniticon name="armmex"/>, 
  then 2 <b>solar panels</b> <uniticon name="armsolar"/>
  followed by making your first factory, which is either a <b>kbot lab</b> <uniticon name="armlab"/> 
  or <b>vehicle plant</b> <uniticon name="armvp"/>.
As a new player, deviating from this build order is highly likely to get you <u>flamed</u>.
You were warned ;D
</p>
<p>
If the map provides much metal, then the player will typically queue the production of a few more basic solar panels.
If metal is more difficult to find, then the player will queue the production of maybe 3-4 <b>advanced solar panels</b> <uniticon name="armadvsol"/> after the first 2 solar panels, 
  because these are more metal-efficient to produce even if they take longer.
You can also start by building <b>wind generators</b> <uniticon name="armwin"/> if the map has a high wind speed.
See the section below on energy production to help determine if this is feasible.
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Queueing Build Orders</title>
<p>
Beginners often make the mistake of trying to build one structure at a time, but this is tedious.
It requires you to spend precious time with each new building as the previous ones are built.
Experienced players will <b>queue</b> the production of several buildings.
To do this, you select a constructor and click the type of item you want to build from its build menu, or use
  a hotkey to select a structure.
Your cursor will change to reflect a grayed picture of the structure to be built.
You can hit <k>ESC</k> to cancel, or click once on the screen to place the building.
For queueing, you will hold down <k>SHIFT</k> before clicking, then drag the cursor across the screen.
You'll see several grayed structures appear on the screen to indicate where the queue will be built.
Release the mouse drag and the constructor will start the build queue. 
The units will be constructed sequentially until they are all built.
</p>

<p>
One of the core balancing skills of the game is to manage the length of your build queues and the amount of build power
  you dedicate to those queues.
We will discuss build power below.
</p>

<p>
<play-tip>
You can use the <k>SHIFT</k> key to <i>append</i> more build orders to the end of a worker's existing build queue.
</play-tip>
</p>

<p>
<play-tip>
You can use the <k>SPACE</k> key to <i>prepend</i> a build order to the start of a worker's existing build queue.
This is a powerful way to make a worker respond quickly to a threat without having to lose its previous queue of orders.
For example, you can prepend the construction of a turret right before an invasion.
When the turret is complete, the worker will resume its previous queue.
</play-tip>
</p>

<p>
Queuing your unit production is a bit different from other RTS games.
Select a lab and left-click on the icons of the different unit types in the build menu until the numbers in the icons
  reach the desired counts for each unit type.
Use right-click to decrease these counts.
You can also use <k>SHIFT</k> while clicking to increment by 5 instead of 1, or use <k>CTRL</k> while clicking to
  increment by 20.
</p>

<p>
Above that, there is a <b>repeat button</b> that defaults to "Off".
Turn this "On" to ensure that the lab will repeat its queue of build orders when it is finished.
Again, this reduces the amount of micromanagement that you need to perform and frees up more of your time to manage the 
  units themselves and other aspects of production.
The lab will build that queue of units indefinitely and your army will grow proportionately according to the unit counts that
  you have provided.
See the basic tactics guide for more information on what units to build and how to use them.
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Assisting and Nano Turrets</title>
<p>
Beginners often overlook the fact that every builder and factory can be <i>assisted</i> by other builders to speed up production.
You actually <b>need</b> to do this in most situations in order to produce units at a competitive rate and to use up your 
  stored resources.
To do this, select some constructors <uniticon name="armck"/> <uniticon name="armcv"/> and then right-click on the building
  that is producing units.
While the building is producing a unit, the constructors will send nano-particles -- increasing its build power.
You can also use this technique to speed up the production of buildings.
Find a constructor that is producing an energy producing building, like a solar panel, wind farm, or advanced solar panel,
  and then select <i>another</i> constructor. 
With the second constructor selected, right click on the first constructor.
This will cause the second to guard the first and automatically assist in any buildings that it is producing.
</p>

<p>
The most important assister unit is called the <b>Nano Turret</b>. 
<uniticon name="armnanotc"/>
This is a small stationary turret that doesn't attack, but automatically assists nearby buildings and constructors.
It gives more build power than a normal constructor while also being more metal-efficient to produce.
Unlike a constructor however, it cannot move around on its own.
Judging when and where to build nano turrets and how many to build is one of the core balancing skills of the game.
It determines the rate of your economic and military growth, the shape of your base, and determines how flexibly
  you can respond to new threats.
Build too few, and you will suffer from excessing, slow production, and inflexibility.
Build too many, and you will spend valuable resources that could be better allocated elsewhere, such as on mobile assisters
  that move around, reclaim metal from wrecks, and can help build "in the field".
</p>

<p>
It is generally better to have too many assisters than too few, but you can still go wrong in this direction!
Remember that different units also require different amounts of "build power", with the later tech tiers
  obviously requiring more.
Experiment often with nano turrets and learn what works for your playing style.
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Reclaiming</title>
<p>
As mentioned in the previous paragraph, your mobile assisters (constructors, assistants) can use the <b>reclaim</b>
  command to reclaim metal from wrecked units after a battle.
To reclaim, select some assisters (or <b>Rezbots</b> <uniticon name="armrectr"/>) and click the reclaim button, then left-click an area and drag outwards,
  forming a circle. 
The reclaimer units will salvage the metal in any wrecks in this circle, adding directly to your metal stores.
</p>

<p>
This is a way to turn a finished battle to your advantage since you can often get most of the metal
  from a dead unit back right away and put it toward production of your own live units.
Also, the early stages of most team games will often see an exploded <b>Commander</b> on the field.
The Commander wreck is always worth full metal: 2500 for BA and 2000 for TechA.
This is a <i>huge</i> amount, and the explosion of a commander (or <b>comm-blast</b>) can be followed by subsequent comm blasts
  as commanders of different teams come to fight for and reclaim that metal!
Often you will not even have enough storage for that much metal, but if you reclaim it and leak, it will go to your allies.
Do not underestimate the power of an team to grow by reclaiming the metal from previous battles.
The author has seen many victories and comebacks emerge from the race to reclaim the metal left after a large clash.
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Energy Production and Energy Economy</title>
<p>
Energy is less competitive to make than metal since it can be made almost anywhere and doesn't require a metal spot.
There are also several alternatives for making it in the early game, including solar, wind, and tidal.
The choice of which to make is very dependent on the map settings and the amount of energy obtained from these sources. 
Press <k>I</k> to view these settings.
Consider the following table:
</p>

<table class="compare" style="margin:auto" border="1" width="600">
  <tr>
     <td width="60"/> <td bgcolor="#00c000">Much more metal efficient than solar</td> 
                      <td bgcolor="#00c0c0">Somewhat more metal efficient than solar</td> 
                      <td bgcolor="#c00000">Less efficient than solar</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
     <td><uniticon name="armwin"/> Wind</td> <td>Wind speed 20 or greater</td>  <td>Wind speed 8-20</td>  <td>Wind speed 7 or less</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
     <td><uniticon name="armtide"/> Tidal </td> <td>Tidal force 50 or greater</td> <td>Tidal force 25-50</td> <td>Tidal force 25 or less</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
<play-tip> The wind speed is also the exact amount of energy produced by a single wind farm.</play-tip>
Most maps that have a high enough wind speed to make wind a viable economic producer also have <i>variable</i> wind speed,
  meaning that the wind can die down reducing your energy output.
</p>
<p>
Note that energy producers that are very <i>efficient</i> in terms of their required metal do not necessarily build as quickly.
In other words, you sometimes pay more metal in order to increase your energy production more quickly.
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Metal Production and Metal Economy</title>
<p>
Metal acquisition is somewhat dependent on the style of map.
There exist special <b>metal maps</b> where every map position contains abundant metal, and a small number of extractors can power vast armies.
On most standard maps however, metal is found in very sparse positions and metal extractors
  can only extract metal at these spots.
Press <b>[F4]</b> to toggle the view of the metal spots on the map.
</p>
<p>
In the early phases of the game, metal is acquired by 
<ul>
  <li>Acquiring territory and building extractors <uniticon name="armmex"/> on metal spots</li>
  <li>Reclaiming the wrecks from units after a battle</li>
  <li>Reclaiming the wreck of a Commander after it explodes</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
In the later phases of the game, metal tends to be <i>produced</i> by large (and fragile) metal-maker buildings. 
<uniticon name="armmmkr"/> 
<uniticon name="cormmkr"/>
These consume a fixed amount of energy and produce a fixed amount of metal.
You can make them at all stages of the game, but the ones produced by the later tech tiers are the most prevalent and important
   (tier 2 in BA, tiers 1.5 and 2 in TechA.)
These produce much more metal than a metal extractor, but they are also fragile and explode a bit when they die.
The tier 2 makers constitute the bulk of metal production for the majority of the middle phases of the game in TechA, and are the only
   source of metal for the middle and late game in BA.
Due to the fact that they deal explosive damage when they die, they are usually built further away from other structures, and 
  usually in a few tightly packed clusters.
These clusters have the property that, if one dies, then they all die.
So bomb your opponent's metal makers!
Target them exclusively if you have a few units left raiding a base!
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Metal Conversion</title>
<p>
The metal makers operate on a "conversion rate" which is really more like a threshold.
You control this threshold using the conversion bar near the top of the screen.
When your energy stores are above the threshold, the makers convert the surplus energy into metal.
Nominally your energy stores will hover around the threshold level as the surplus is converted into metal.
If your energy stores instead go to their maximum, it's time to construct more metal makers.
</p>

<p>
The threshold level can be changed for various reasons.
When the map is very windy, you want to keep some energy in store for when the wind dies down, 
  so the threshold can be set high to provide a "buffer" a large amount of energy.
Another reason for setting the level high is so that the player will have energy in store for short bursts of use by weapons
  such as the Commander D-Gun, the big ARM T2 Annihilator turret <uniticon name="armanni"/>, or the ARM Snipers <uniticon name="armsnipe"/>. 
</p>

<p>
When player is building finishing a large structure, he typically wants to use as much metal as he can, so he sets the threshold low.
Often the completion of a new fus or afus will result in more income than the player can use right away, so you can avoid excessing
  by setting the threshold low shortly before completion.
This gives the extra metal needed for fast completion of the producer and also depletes energy storage in preparation for
  the large increase in energy income upon its completion.
</p>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Rushing and Balanced Growth</title>
<p>
In a very large game, you will often see some players dedicating their resources entirely to the 
  production of even more resource gathering, usually for the purpose of climbing the tech tree more quickly.
Many see it as more favourable for the back players to grow their economy and achieve higher tech earlier
  in the game, hoping to dominate the opposing side with the support of a superior economy.
</p>

<p>
Another strategy common among stronger players is to build the minimal economy necessary to support the production 
  of a specific squad of early units that can yield a devastating attack.
"Early" can mean at the very beginning of the game, as with a fast Flea or Peewee rush, or it can mean in a 
  later phase of the game by achieving the production of a high-tech unit that can dominate lower-tiered units easily, 
  such as a Goliath rush.
</p>

<p>
Both of these extreme economic strategies are casually referred to as <b>rushing</b>, either as 
  <b>rushing tech</b>, <b>rushing a particular unit</b>, or sometimes <b>rushing an afus</b>, the latter
  in reference to powerful T2 advanced fusions  <uniticon name="aafus"/> which generate enormous energy and can support 
  both more advanced units and enormous unit production capacity.
<span class="techa-tip">
In the TechA world, tech rushing is practically the norm since the tech tiers are expensive and have the
  tendency to dominate lower tiers more easily.
Read <a href="techa-basic-tech">here</a> for more information about tech growth in TechA.
This, combined with the tendency in TechA for games to be played on much larger maps, means that early attacks 
  can easily be foiled by superior technology by the time the attacking units reach the (more distant) enemy encampments.
</span>
</p>

<p>
Ironically, a strong player achieves balanced growth by alternating between rushing specific resource production buildings
  followed by rushing specific squads of units.
This is considered highly efficient since the desired target buildings or units are achieved in the shortest time possible, 
  meaning that the player can focus all their economic power on specific targets in sequence, rather than having this power 
  divided between several build targets.
The latter strategy results in slower achievement of the build orders .
</p>

</section>

</chapter>
